I work with children with autism.
أعمل مع أطفال يعانون من التوحد.
Specifically, I make technologies
بالتحديد أنا أصنع تقنيات
to help them communicate.
تساعدهم على التواصل.
Now, many of the problems that children
الآن، العديد من المشاكلات التي تواجه الأطفال المصابين بالتوحد
with autism face, they have a common source,
لها سبب واحد،
and that source is that they find it difficult
وذلك السبب هو أنهم يجدون صعوبة
to understand abstraction, symbolism.
في فهم التعبيرات الرمزية، والتعبيرات التجريدية
And because of this, they have a lot of difficulty with language.
وبسبب ذلك فهم يواجهون العديد من الصعوبات مع اللغات.
Let me tell you a little bit about why this is.
دعوني أخبركم قليلاً عن السبب.
You see that this is a picture of a bowl of soup.
ترون هذه الصورة إنها لزبدية من الحساء.
All of us can see it. All of us understand this.
جمعينا نستطيع رؤيتها، جميعنا نستطيع فهمها.
These are two other pictures of soup,
وهاتان صورتان أخريتان للحساء،
but you can see that these are more abstract
ولكن بمقدوركم رؤية أن هاتين الصورتين أكثر تجريدية
These are not quite as concrete.
وليست تمامًا كصورة زبدية الحساء في الواقع.
And when you get to language,
وعندما يتعلق الامر باللغة،
you see that it becomes a word
فإن الصور تتحول الى كلمة
whose look, the way it looks and the way it sounds,
ومنظر الكلمة، الطريقة التي تظهر بها الكلمة ووقعها،
has absolutely nothing to do with what it started with,
ليس لها علاقة بنشأتها وأصلها،
or what it represents, which is the bowl of soup.
وبما تمثله، وهو طبق الحساء.
So it's essentially a completely abstract,
إذا هي أساسا رمز تجريدي،
a completely arbitrary representation of something
طريقة لتمثيل شيء ما
which is in the real world,
موجود في عالمنا،
and this is something that children with autism
والأطفال المصابون بالتوحد
have an incredible amount of difficulty with.
يجدون صعوبة بالغة في التعامل مع هذا الأمر.
Now that's why most of the people that work with children with autism --
ولهذا السبب أغلب الناس الذين يتعاملون مع الأطفال المصابين بالتوحد -
speech therapists, educators --
الأخصائيون اللغويون والمعلمون -
what they do is, they try to help children with autism
ما يفعلونه هو محاولة مساعدة الأطفال المصابين بالتوحد
communicate not with words, but with pictures.
للتواصل مع الآخرين ليس بالكلمات وإنما بالصور.
So if a child with autism wanted to say,
لذا إذا أراد طفل مصاب بالتوحد أن يقول،
"I want soup," that child would pick
"أنا أريد حساء" سيختار هذا الطفل
three different pictures, "I," "want," and "soup,"
ثلاث صور مختلفة لتمثيل كلامة "أنا" و"أريد" و"حساء"،
and they would put these together,
وسيضعها مع بعضها البعض،
and then the therapist or the parent would
وبالتالي سيفهم الاخصائيون والآباء
understand that this is what the kid wants to say.
ما يريد الطفل أي يقوله لهم.
And this has been incredibly effective;
وهذا الأسلوب كان فعالا للغاية؛
for the last 30, 40 years
خلال ال 30، وال 40 سنة الماضية
people have been doing this.
كان الناس يستخدمون هذه الطريقة.
In fact, a few years back,
في الواقع منذ عدة سنوات،
I developed an app for the iPad
قمت أنا بتطوير برنامج لجهاز (الأيباد)
which does exactly this. It's called Avaz,
يقوم بنفس الأمر، ويدعى أفاز،
and the way it works is that kids select
وطريقة عمله هي أن الطفل يقوم باختيار
different pictures.
صور مختلفة.
These pictures are sequenced together to form sentences,
ويتم ترتيب هذه الصور مع بعضها البعض لتكوين جملة،
and these sentences are spoken out.
ويقوم البرنامج بنطق هذه الجمل.
So Avaz is essentially converting pictures,
فبالتالي البرنامج أساسا محول للصور،
it's a translator, it converts pictures into speech.
يعمل كمترجم، يقوم بتحويل الصور إلى كلام.
Now, this was very effective.
والآن البرنامج فعال للغاية،
There are thousands of children using this,
هناك الآلاف من الأطفال الذين يستخدمونه،
you know, all over the world,
من جميع أنحاء العالم،
and I started thinking about
وهذا دفعني لأفكر في
what it does and what it doesn't do.
ما يقوم البرنامج بعمله وما لا يقوم البرنامج بعمله.
And I realized something interesting:
وأدركت شيئا مثيرا للاهتمام:
Avaz helps children with autism learn words.
"avaz"يقوم بمساعدة الأطفال المصابين بالتوحد ليتعلموا الكلمات.
What it doesn't help them do is to learn
ما لا يساعدهم البرنامج على تعلمه هو معرفة
word patterns.
أنماط الكلمات.
Let me explain this in a little more detail.
دعوني أشرح بتفصيل أكثر.
Take this sentence: "I want soup tonight."
فمثلا هذه الجملة: "أريد حساء الليلة".
Now it's not just the words here that convey the meaning.
ليست الكلمات هنا فقط هي من تحمل معنى الجملة.
It's also the way in which these words are arranged,
بل أيضا ترتيب هذه الكلمات،
the way these words are modified and arranged.
طريقة ترتيب وتعديل الكلمات.
And that's why a sentence like "I want soup tonight"
ولهذا فإن جملة مثل: "أريد حساء الليلة".
is different from a sentence like
مختلفة عن جملة مثل
"Soup want I tonight," which is completely meaningless.
"حساء أريد أنا الليلة" وهذه الجملة لا معنى لها.
So there is another hidden abstraction here
وهنا يوجد نوع مختفي من أنواع التجريد
which children with autism find a lot of difficulty coping with,
ويجد الأطفال المصابون بالتوحد صعوبة في في التعامل مع هذا النوع،
and that's the fact that you can modify words
والتجريد هنا هو إمكانية تعديل الكلمات
and you can arrange them to have
وإمكانية ترتيب الكلمات لتحصل على
different meanings, to convey different ideas.
معاني مختلفة للكلمات، لتوصيل أفكار مختلفة.
Now, this is what we call grammar.
وهذا مايعرف ب (النحو) في اللغة.
And grammar is incredibly powerful,
والنحو له قوة رهيبة،
because grammar is this one component of language
ولأن النحو هو أحد مكونات اللغة التي
which takes this finite vocabulary that all of us have
تأخذ العدد المحدود من المفردات التي نعرفها
and allows us to convey an infinite amount of information,
وتحولها إلى عدد غير محدود من المعلومات والجمل،
an infinite amount of ideas.
وعدد غير محدود من الأفكار.
It's the way in which you can put things together
إنها طريقة تركيبك للجمل مع بعض
in order to convey anything you want to.
حتى تعطي أي معلومة تريد أنت ايصالها.
And so after I developed Avaz,
ولذا بعد أن قمت بتطوير برنامجي أفاز،
I worried for a very long time
كنت قلقًا لقترة طويلة بشأن
about how I could give grammar to children with autism.
كيفية تقديم قواعد النحو لللأطفال المصابين بالتوحد.
The solution came to me from a very interesting perspective.
جاءت لي فكرة الحل من منظور مثير للاهتمام.
I happened to chance upon a child with autism
وما حدث أني شهدت طفلة مصابة بالتوحد
conversing with her mom,
تتحدث مع أمها،
and this is what happened.
وهذا ما حدث.
Completely out of the blue, very spontaneously,
فجأة وبدون أي مقدمات.
the child got up and said, "Eat."
قامت الطفلة وقالت "أكل".
Now what was interesting was
الأمر المثير للاهتمام كان
the way in which the mom was trying to tease out
بطريقةٍ ما كانت الأم تحاول أن تستنبط
the meaning of what the child wanted to say
ما تريد ابنتها أن تقوله
by talking to her in questions.
عن طريق الأسئلة.
So she asked, "Eat what? Do you want to eat ice cream?
فسألت ابنتها "ماذا تأكلين؟ هل تريدين أن تأكلي المثلجات؟
You want to eat? Somebody else wants to eat?
هل تريدي أن تأكلي؟ أهناك شخص آخر يريد أن يأكل؟
You want to eat cream now? You want to eat ice cream in the evening?"
هل تريدي أن تأكلي المثلجات الآن؟ هل تريدين أن تأكلي المثلجات الليلة؟"
And then it struck me that
الآن ما فعلته الأم صعقني
what the mother had done was something incredible.
ما فعلته الأم كان شيئًا لا يصدق.
She had been able to get that child to communicate
كانت تستطيع أن تجعل طفلتها توصل
an idea to her without grammar.
فكرتها لأمها بدون قواعد النحو.
And it struck me that maybe this is what
وصعقني أن هذا ما
I was looking for.
كنت أبحث عنه.
Instead of arranging words in an order, in sequence,
بدلا من أن تضع الكلمات بالترتيب،
as a sentence, you arrange them
كجملة، سترتبهم
in this map, where they're all linked together
في هذه الخريطة، حيث أن جميع الكلمات ليست مرتبطة ببعضها البعض
not by placing them one after the other
كلمة كلمة بالتوالي
but in questions, in question-answer pairs.
ولكنها مرتبطة ببعضها البعض على هيئة إجابات أسئلة.
And so if you do this, then what you're conveying
إذا حين تطبق هذه الفكرة، ما سيتضح ليس
is not a sentence in English,
جملة باللغة الإنجليزية، ولكن
but what you're conveying is really a meaning,
ما سيتضح حقيقةً هو معنى،
the meaning of a sentence in English.
المطلوب من الجملة.
Now, meaning is really the underbelly, in some sense, of language.
إذا المعنى في الأساس هو المغزى من أي لغة.
It's what comes after thought but before language.
هو ما يخطر في ذهنك بعد الفكرة ولكن قبل اللغة.
And the idea was that this particular representation
والفكرة هي أن هذا التمثيل المعين للكلمة
might convey meaning in its raw form.
يعطي معنى للجملة في أبسط صورة.
So I was very excited by this, you know,
لقد كنت متحمسا للغاية حيال تلك الفكرة،
hopping around all over the place,
أجرب هذا وذاك
trying to figure out if I can convert
محاولا أن أكتشف هل بالإمكان تحويل
all possible sentences that I hear into this.
كل جملة أسمعها إلى هذا.
And I found that this is not enough.
واكتشفت أن ذلك ليس كافيًا.
Why is this not enough?
لماذا ليس كافيًا؟
This is not enough because if you wanted to convey
ليس كافيًا لأنك لو أردت أن تصور
something like negation,
شيئًا مرفوضًا،
you want to say, "I don't want soup,"
مثلاً تريد أن تقول:"أنا لا أريد حساءً"
then you can't do that by asking a question.
إذا لا يمكنك استخدام مبدأ الأسئلة في هذه الحالة.
You do that by changing the word "want."
لا يمكنك عمل هذا عن طريق الأسئلة ولكن عن طريق تغيير الكلمة"أريد".
Again, if you wanted to say,
مرة أخرى إذا أردت أن تقول،
"I wanted soup yesterday,"
"أنا أردتُ حساءً أمس"،
you do that by converting the word "want" into "wanted."
يمكنك فعل هذا عن طريق تحويل الكلمة "أريد" إلى"أردت".
It's a past tense.
الكلمة فعل ماضٍ.
So this is a flourish which I added
فقمت بعمل إضافة للبرنامج.
to make the system complete.
لجعل النظام تامًا.
This is a map of words joined together
هذه خريطة لكلمات تم إضافتها معًا
as questions and answers,
كسؤال وإجابة،
and with these filters applied on top of them
ومع هذه الإضافة تطبق فوق كل كلمة
in order to modify them to represent
حتى نعدل الكلمة فتمثل
certain nuances.
هذه الفروق البسيطة
Let me show you this with a different example.
دعوني أوضح لكم بمثال آخر.
Let's take this sentence:
لنأخذ هذه الجملة:
"I told the carpenter I could not pay him."
"أخبرت النجار بأنني لا أستطيع أن أدفع المال له"
It's a fairly complicated sentence.
إنها جملة معقدة إلى حدٍّ ما.
The way that this particular system works,
طريقة عمل هذه الإضافة هي،
you can start with any part of this sentence.
بإمكانك البدء بأي جزء من الجملة.
I'm going to start with the word "tell."
سأبدأ بالكلمة "أخبرت".
So this is the word "tell."
إذا هذه الكلمة "يخبر"
Now this happened in the past,
حدثت في الماضي،
so I'm going to make that "told."
فسأستخدم الكلمة "أخبرت"
Now, what I'm going to do is,
ما سأفعله هو،
I'm going to ask questions.
سوف أقوم بطرح أسئلة.
So, who told? I told.
إذا، من أخبر؟ أنا أخبرت.
I told whom? I told the carpenter.
أخبرت من؟ أخبرت النجار.
Now we start with a different part of the sentence.
الآن نأخذ جزء آخر من الجملة.
We start with the word "pay,"
نأخذ الكلمة "يدفع".
and we add the ability filter to it to make it "can pay."
ثم نضع إضافتي فوق الكلمة فتصبح "يستطيع الدفع".
Then we make it "can't pay,"
ونجعلها "لا يستطيع الدفع"،
and we can make it "couldn't pay"
ومن ثم نجعلها "لم أستطع الدفع"
by making it the past tense.
عن طريق تحويلها لصيغة الماضي
So who couldn't pay? I couldn't pay.
إذا من لم يستطيع الدفع؟ أنا لم أستطع الدفع.
Couldn't pay whom? I couldn't pay the carpenter.
لم تستطع أن تدفع أجرة من؟ لم أستطع أن أدفع أجرة النجار.
And then you join these two together
ومن ثم تضيف ما سبق عمله إلى بعضه البعض
by asking this question:
عن طريق استخدام هذا السؤال:
What did I tell the carpenter?
ماذا قلت للنجار؟
I told the carpenter I could not pay him.
أخبرت النجار بأنني لم أستطيع دفع أجرته.
Now think about this. This is
الآن فكروا في الأمر. هذا
—(Applause)—
- (تصفيق) -
this is a representation of this sentence
هذا تمثيل لهذه الجملة
without language.
بدون استخدام للغة.
And there are two or three interesting things about this.
وهناك شيئان أو ثلاثة أشياء مثيرة للاهتمام هنا.
First of all, I could have started anywhere.
أولها كان بإمكاني البدء من أي مكان.
I didn't have to start with the word "tell."
لم يكن هناك حاجة للبدء بالكلمة "يخبر".
I could have started anywhere in the sentence,
كان بإمكاني البدء بأي جزء من الجملة.
and I could have made this entire thing.
وكان بإمكاني تطبيق هذا في جزء من الجملة.
The second thing is, if I wasn't an English speaker,
الشيء الآخر هو لو لم أكن أتحدث بالإنجليزية،
if I was speaking in some other language,
لو كنت أتحدث بأية لغة أخرى،
this map would actually hold true in any language.
كانت هذه الخريطة لتعمل أيضًا بأية لغة أخرى.
So long as the questions are standardized,
طالما أن مبدأ الأسئلة مُطبّق،
the map is actually independent of language.
الخريطة منفصلة عن اللغة تمامًا.
So I call this FreeSpeech,
لذا قمت بتسمية الفكرة بFreeSpeech.
and I was playing with this for many, many months.
و كنت أستخدم التطبيق لشهور عديدة.
I was trying out so many different combinations of this.
وكنت أجرب العديد من تركيبات الكلمات المختلفة.
And then I noticed something very interesting about FreeSpeech.
ولاحظت شيئًا مثيرًا في FreeSpeech.
I was trying to convert language,
كنت أحاول تحويل اللغات،
convert sentences in English into sentences in FreeSpeech,
أحول الجمل من اللغة الانجليزية إلى جمل في FreeSpeech
and vice versa, and back and forth.
والعكس بالعكس.
And I realized that this particular configuration,
وأدركت أن هذه الطريقة الخاصة،
this particular way of representing language,
في تمثيل وترتيب اللغة،
it allowed me to actually create very concise rules
أهّلتني لإنشاء قواعد مختصرة
that go between FreeSpeech on one side
يمكن تطبيقها على FreeSpeech من جهة
and English on the other.
وعلى اللغة الإنجليزية من جهة أخرى.
So I could actually write this set of rules
فكان بإمكاني كتابة مجموعة من القواعد
that translates from this particular representation into English.
التي تحول من تمثيل معين إلى اللغة الإنجليزية.
And so I developed this thing.
وأيضا قمت بتطوير ذلك الشيء.
I developed this thing called the FreeSpeech Engine
ذلك الشيء الذي يدعى محرك FreeSpeech
which takes any FreeSpeech sentence as the input
الذي يأخذ أي جملة من FreeSpeech كمدخل
and gives out perfectly grammatical English text.
ويخرج نصا باللغة الإنجليزية صحيحا نحويا.
And by putting these two pieces together,
وعن طريق وضع هذين الجزئين مع بعض،
the representation and the engine,
تمثيل الكلمة والمحرك،
I was able to create an app, a technology for children with autism,
كنت قادرا على إنشاء برنامج متطور للأطفال المصابين بالتوحد،
that not only gives them words
هذا البرنامج لم يوفر لهم الكلمات فقط
but also gives them grammar.
ولكن أتاح لهم النحو أيضا.
So I tried this out with kids with autism,
وقد قمت بتجربة البرنامج مع الأطفال المصابين بالتوحد،
and I found that there was an incredible amount of identification.
واكتشفت الكم الهائل من التطابق.
They were able to create sentences in FreeSpeech
كان بمقدرة الأطفال إنشاء جمل في FreeSpeech
which were much more complicated but much more effective
وتلك الجمل كانت أكثر تعقيدًا ولكن أقوى
than equivalent sentences in English,
في معناها عن تلك الجمل المكافئة لها في اللغة الإنجليزية،
and I started thinking about
وبدأت أفكر في
why that might be the case.
ما قد يكون السبب.
And I had an idea, and I want to talk to you about this idea next.
وكانت لدي فكرة، وأريد أن أحدثكم عنها لاحقًا.
In about 1997, about 15 years back,
حوالي عام 1997، تقريبا منذ 15 سنة.
there were a group of scientists that were trying
كانت هناك مجموعة من العلماء تحاول
to understand how the brain processes language,
أن تفهم كيف يعالج العقل البشري اللغات،
and they found something very interesting.
واكتشفوا أمرًا مثيرًا للاهتمام.
They found that when you learn a language
وجدوا أنه عندما تتعلم لغة جديدة
as a child, as a two-year-old,
كطفل، عمره سنتان
you learn it with a certain part of your brain,
تتعلمها بجزء معين في دماغك،
and when you learn a language as an adult --
ولكن عندما تتعلمها كشخص بالغ -
for example, if I wanted to learn Japanese right now —
مثلا إذا أردت أن تتعلم اليابانية الآن -
a completely different part of my brain is used.
فإن دماغك يستخدم جزء آخر تماما.
Now I don't know why that's the case,
أنا لا أعرف السبب في هذه الحالة،
but my guess is that that's because
ولكن تخميني هو لأنه
when you learn a language as an adult,
عندما تتعلم اللغة كشخص بالغ،
you almost invariably learn it
فأنت تقريبا تتعلمها
through your native language, or through your first language.
عن طريق لغتك الأصلية
So what's interesting about FreeSpeech
الأمر المثير للاهتمام حول FreeSpeech
is that when you create a sentence
هو أنه عندما تنشئ جملة ما
or when you create language,
عندما يقوم طفل مصاب بالتوحد،
a child with autism creates language with FreeSpeech,
بإنشاء جملة ما باستخدام FreeSpeech،
they're not using this support language,
فالأطفال لا يستخدمون لغتهم الأولى،
they're not using this bridge language.
لا يستخدمون لغتهم الأم كوصلة.
They're directly constructing the sentence.
هم ينشئون هذه الجمل مباشرةً.
And so this gave me this idea.
الأمر الذي أوحى لي بفكرة.
Is it possible to use FreeSpeech
هل من الممكن استخدام FreeSpeech
not for children with autism
ليس فقط مع الأطفال المصابين بالتوحد
but to teach language to people without disabilities?
وإنما لتعليم باقي الناس اللغات بدون إعاقات أو جسور؟
And so I tried a number of experiments.
لذا قمت بعدد من التجارب.
The first thing I did was I built a jigsaw puzzle
وأول شيء قمت به هو عمل أحجية صور
in which these questions and answers
وعلى القطع بعض أسئلة الجمل وإجاباتها
are coded in the form of shapes,
على هيئة أشكال مختلفة،
in the form of colors,
ولها ألوان متعددة،
and you have people putting these together
والناس يقومون بترتيبها مع بعضها البعض
and trying to understand how this works.
ويحاولون فهم مغزى هذه الصور.
And I built an app out of it, a game out of it,
ومن هذه الفكرة أنشأت برنامجًا، لعبة،
in which children can play with words
وبها يلعب الأطفال مع الكلمات
and with a reinforcement,
ومع الدعم،
a sound reinforcement of visual structures,
مع الدعم الصوتي لتلك الأشكال،
they're able to learn language.
كان بإمكانهم تعلم اللغات.
And this, this has a lot of potential, a lot of promise,
وهذه الفكرة لها العديد من القدرات وهي فكرة واعدة،
and the government of India recently
وقد قامت الحكومة الهندية مؤخرًا
licensed this technology from us,
بترخيص هذه التنكولوجيا لنا،
and they're going to try it out with millions of different children
وسوف يجربونها مع ملايين الأطفال
trying to teach them English.
محاولين أن يعلموهم اللغة الإنجليزية.
And the dream, the hope, the vision, really,
والحلم والأمل والهدف الحقيقي،
is that when they learn English this way,
هو أ،ه حين يتعلمون الإنجليزية بهذه الطريقة،
they learn it with the same proficiency
فإنهم يتعلمونها بنفس الكفائة
as their mother tongue.
كما لو أنها لغتهم الأم.
All right, let's talk about something else.
حسنًا إذا، لنتكلم عن أمر آخر.
Let's talk about speech.
لنتكلم عن التخاطب.
This is speech.
هذا هو التخاطب.
So speech is the primary mode of communication
التخاطب هو الطريقة الأساسية للتواصل
delivered between all of us.
بيننا.
Now what's interesting about speech is that
المثير للاهتمام في التخاطب هو
speech is one-dimensional.
أن التخاطب له بعٌد واحد
Why is it one-dimensional?
لماذا يعد التخاطب أحادي البعد؟
It's one-dimensional because it's sound.
يعد التخاطب أحادي البعد لأنه صوت.
It's also one-dimensional because
و هو أيضًا أحادي البعد لأن
our mouths are built that way.
أفواههنا مخلوقة بهذه الطريقة.
Our mouths are built to create one-dimensional sound.
أفواهنا مصممة لعمل صوت أحادي البعد.
But if you think about the brain,
ولكن حينما تفكر في الدماغ،
the thoughts that we have in our heads
الأفكار في أدمغتنا
are not one-dimensional.
ليست أحادية البعد.
I mean, we have these rich,
أقصد بذلك لدينا في عقولنا تلك،
complicated, multi-dimensional ideas.
الأفكار الغنية والمعقدة والمتعددة الأبعاد.
Now, it seems to me that language
تبدو لي اللغات
is really the brain's invention
وكأنها ابتكار للدماغ
to convert this rich, multi-dimensional thought
لتحويل هذه الأفكار الغنية والمتعددة الأبعاد
on one hand
في كفة
into speech on the other hand.
إلى محادثة في كفة أخرى.
Now what's interesting is that
الملفت للانتباه هو
we do a lot of work in information nowadays,
اليوم نحن نقوم بكثير من العمل على المعلومات،
and almost all of that is done in the language domain.
وأغلب هذا يتم في مجال لغوي.
Take Google, for example.
على سبيل المثال جوجل مثلا.
Google trawls all these countless billions of websites,
تضم جوجل مليارات المواقع الإلكترونية الغير معدودة،
all of which are in English, and when you want to use Google,
هذه المواقع باللغة الانجليزية، وحينما تريد استخدام "جوجل"
you go into Google search, and you type in English,
ستذهب إلى "جوجل" وتبحث ب استخدام اللغة الإنجليزية،
and it matches the English with the English.
وسيطابق "جوجل" ما كتبته أنت بالإنجليزية بما يوجد على الشبكة بالإنجليزية.
What if we could do this in FreeSpeech instead?
ماذا لو استخدمنا FreeSpeech بدلاً من التقنية المُستدمة حاليًا؟
I have a suspicion that if we did this,
لدي شكوك أننا لو قمنا بذلك،
we'd find that algorithms like searching,
فإن الخوارزميات الخاصة بالبحث،
like retrieval, all of these things,
والاستعادة، وكل هذه الأمور،
are much simpler and also more effective,
ستكون أبسط وأكثر كفاءة،
because they don't process the data structure of speech.
لأنها لا تحتاج إلى معالجة بيانات الكلام.
Instead they're processing the data structure of thought.
في المقابل تعالج هيكلة بيانات الأفكار.
The data structure of thought.
هيكلة بيانات الأفكار.
That's a provocative idea.
إنها فكرة محضة.
But let's look at this in a little more detail.
ولكن لنلقي نظرة بتفصيل أكثر.
So this is the FreeSpeech ecosystem.
هذا نظام FreeSpeech.
We have the Free Speech representation on one side,
لدينا هنا نظام FreeSpeech من جهة،
and we have the FreeSpeech Engine, which generates English.
ولدينا محرك FreeSpeech الذي يكون الجمل الانجليزية.
Now if you think about it,
إذا فكرتم حيال الأمر،
FreeSpeech, I told you, is completely language-independent.
FreeSpeech غير مرتبط باللغة.
It doesn't have any specific information in it
ولا تحتوي على أي معلومات مخصصة لشيء ما بداخلها
which is about English.
على عكس اللغة الإنجليزية.
So everything that this system knows about English
فكل ما يعرفه النظام عن اللغة الإنجليزية
is actually encoded into the engine.
في الواقع مشفر داخل المحرك.
That's a pretty interesting concept in itself.
هذا المفهوم في حد ذاته مثير للاهتمام.
You've encoded an entire human language
لقد قمت بتحويل لغة البشر بأكملها
into a software program.
إلى برنامج.
But if you look at what's inside the engine,
ولكن إذا نظرت بداخل المحرك،
it's actually not very complicated.
تجد أنه غير معقد.
It's not very complicated code.
ليس بكود معقد.
And what's more interesting is the fact that
والمثير أيضًا هو أن
the vast majority of the code in that engine
الأغلبية العظمى من كود المحرك
is not really English-specific.
ليس خاصا بالإنجليزية فقط.
And that gives this interesting idea.
الأمر الذي أوحى لي بفكرة مثيرة للاهتمام.
It might be very easy for us to actually
ربما أستطيع إنشاء هذه المحركات
create these engines in many, many different languages,
للعديد من اللغات الأخرى،
in Hindi, in French, in German, in Swahili.
باللغة الهندية والفرنسية والألمانية والسواحيلية.
And that gives another interesting idea.
وذلك أيضا أوحى لي بفكرة أخرى مثيرة للاهتمام.
For example, supposing I was a writer,
مثلا، لنفرض أني كاتب،
say, for a newspaper or for a magazine.
في جريدة مثلا أو مجلة.
I could create content in one language, FreeSpeech,
من الممكن لي ككاتب إنشاء المقال الخاص بي باستخدام FreeSpeech،
and the person who's consuming that content,
والشخص الذي سيحصل على مقالي،
the person who's reading that particular information
الشخص الذي سيقرأ هذه المعلومة
could choose any engine,
بإمكانه اختيار أي محرك،
and they could read it in their own mother tongue,
وهؤلاء الأشخاص بإمكانهم بالتالي قراءة هذه المادة بلغتهم الأم،
in their native language.
بلغتهم الأصلية.
I mean, this is an incredibly attractive idea,
وهذه الفكرة رائعة جدًا،
especially for India.
خصوصًا في الهند.
We have so many different languages.
لدينا العديد من اللغات المختلفة.
There's a song about India, and there's a description
هناك أغنية عن الهند تصف
of the country as, it says,
لنا البلد، تقول...
(in Sanskrit).
(بالسنسكريتية)
That means "ever-smiling speaker
تعني "المتحدث المبتسم دوما
of beautiful languages."
للغة جميلة"
Language is beautiful.
اللغة هي شيء جميل.
I think it's the most beautiful of human creations.
أعتقد أنها أجمل إبداع قام به البشر.
I think it's the loveliest thing that our brains have invented.
وألطف شيء قامت عقولنا بابتكاره.
It entertains, it educates, it enlightens,
إنها تمتع وتُعلم وتنير العقول،
but what I like the most about language
ولكن أكثر ما أحبه بخصوص اللغة
is that it empowers.
هي أنها تزيدنا قوة.
I want to leave you with this.
أريد أن أنهي حديثي.
This is a photograph of my collaborators,
بهذه الصورة للسيدات اللاتي قمن بمساعدتي،
my earliest collaborators
أوائل المساعدات.
when I started working on language
عندما بدأت أعمل على اللغة
and autism and various other things.
والتوحد وبعض الأشياء الأخرى.
The girl's name is Pavna,
هذه الفتاة تدعى بافنا،
and that's her mother, Kalpana.
وهذه أمها كالبانا.
And Pavna's an entrepreneur,
وبافنا رائدة أعمال،
but her story is much more remarkable than mine,
ولكن قصة حياتها أروع من قصتي بكثير..
because Pavna is about 23.
لإن بافنا عمرها 23 سنة.
She has quadriplegic cerebral palsy,
وهي مصابة بشلل كامل في الدماغ،
so ever since she was born,
منذ أن ولدت،
she could neither move nor talk.
لم يكن بإمكانها التحرك أو الكلام.
And everything that she's accomplished so far,
وكل ما أنجزته إلى الآن.
finishing school, going to college,
إنهاء المدرسة، والالتحاق بالجامعة،
starting a company,
وإنشاء شركة،
collaborating with me to develop Avaz,
مساعدتي لتطوير أفاز،
all of these things she's done
كل هذا تم
with nothing more than moving her eyes.
عن طريق تحريك عينيها فقط.
Daniel Webster said this:
دانيل وبستر قال:
He said, "If all of my possessions were taken
"لو أخذ مني كل ما أملكه
from me with one exception,
باستثناء شيء واحد،
I would choose to keep the power of communication,
سأختار الاحتفاظ بالقدرة على التواصل،
for with it, I would regain all the rest."
وبها سأستعيد باقي ما أخذ مني".
And that's why, of all of these incredible applications of FreeSpeech,
ولذا فإن أكثر ميزة أحبها من بين جميع ميزات تطبيق FreeSpeech الرائعة،
the one that's closest to my heart
أقربها إلى قلبي
still remains the ability for this
هي القدرة على
to empower children with disabilities
منح الأطفال ذوي الإعاقات
to be able to communicate,
إمكانية التواصل،
the power of communication,
القدرة على التواصل،
to get back all the rest.
التي ستساعدهم على استرجاع الباقي.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرًا لكم. (تصفيق)
Thank you. Thank you. Thank you. (Applause)
شكرًا لكم، شكرًا لكم. (تصفيق)